公元1529年冬 红衣大主教沃尔西逃到
埃舍尔避难 但安妮 博林及其叔父
诺尔福克公爵 却想赶他一路向北
远离国王陛下的视线
托马斯 克伦威尔 沃尔西的死忠拥护者
留在了伦敦 为他的主人
寻求权力复出的机会
本字幕由大家字幕组原创翻译制作仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为若因私自散布传播造成法律问题 本字幕组概不负责更多影视请搜索并关注新浪微博  大家字幕组
翻译：被中出的骁骁  星星美少女 小俊仔儿
翻译：抹茶苏 汉谟拉 水水儿  Cindy
时间轴：静宇  Sandra恨MKV  压制：大汪不开森   校对：被中出的骁骁
狼・厅
第1季 第2集
谢谢
Thank you.
我拒绝谈论红衣主教之事
I can't talk about the Cardinal.
-陛下... -不行 你听不明白吗?
-Your Majesty... -No. Don't you understand?
这件事根本没有回旋的余地
I can't talk about him.
何必又碰一鼻子灰
Here again.
噢 史蒂芬
Stephen.
等了很长时间吧?
You been waiting long?
没等他 我只是沉浸在国王要和我见面的恩典中无法自拔
Well, I was under the impression I had an interview with the King.
再一次
Again.
没错 再一次
是啊
Yes.
捉摸不透啊 是吧?
Elusive, isn't he?
你还觉得你自己很受宠吗?
Did you think yourself a special favourite?
一只猫生了一窝幼崽
A cat has had her litter,
就在我的房间这里
here, in my rooms.
瞧你哟!
Look at it!
漆黑如恶魔撒旦
Black as the devil,
就在我的床下 它出世了
born right here, under my very bed.
你说这是不是我们这次远行的凶兆呢?
How's that for a bad omen before a journey?
您不应该离开
You shouldn't leave.
托马斯 当诺尔福克威胁说要撕碎我的时候...
Merry Thomas, when Norfolk threatens to bite...
也由不得我不离开了
.. it's time to be gone.
您是不会喜爱北方的
You won't like the north.
我可是约克的大主教
I am the Archbishop of York.
虽如此 但您从未到过北方 而我去过
Yes, but you've never been. I have.
那里民风彪悍 荒蛮未开
Filthy weather, people, morals.
但国王想要我远离啊
The King wants me gone.
他想让我蒙羞
He wants to humiliate me.
也觉得这算是给罗马教皇一个警告
Thinks it sends a sharp message to the Pope.
我就像凯瑟琳王后一样...
I feel like Katherine...
被罢黜了
.. cast off.
但依然敬爱他
But still, I love him.
我们还能做什么呢?
What will we do?
收买人心
Bribe people.
您还有土地
You still have land.
即使国王查抄了您的全部身家 百姓仍会自问
Even if the King takes everything you have, people will ask themselves,
"他真的会轻易将教会的所属物交出吗？"
"Can he truly give what belongs to the church?"
除非是经过您的首肯 不然他们的头衔也名不正言不顺
No-one will be sure of their title unless you confirm it.
所以主人您仍然...
So you see, my Lord, you still...
- 您仍然有王牌在手  - 确实如此
- You still have cards in your hand. - Yes.
但是 说起来...
And after all...
欲加之罪 何患无辞...
.. if he wants to bring a treason...
如果国王意欲将叛国罪强加于您
If the King meant to charge you with treason,
- 您现在怕是早已在象牙塔里了 不是吗?  - 没错
- you'd be in the tower now, wouldn't you?       - Yes.
国王仍牵挂您
He misses you.
您会重获圣宠的
You'll return to favour.
一条新生命
New life,
诞生在您的床下
born under your very bed?
要我说 这是大吉之兆
Well... I'd read that as a good omen.
呵呵 真是巧舌如簧呢
Ah, you lawyer.
看看谁在圣诞节归来了
Look who's back for Christmas.
这是什么 格雷戈里 总算长胡子了？
What's this, Gregory,some kind of beard?
我在培根的反面 可见过更多的毛
Think I've seen more hair on a side of bacon.
格雷戈里说我们能在大厅里遛狗
Gregory says we can race his dogs up and down the hall.
- 父亲大人  - 欢迎回家 格雷戈里
- Father.   - Welcome home, Gregory.
那是设计完美的棋局
That was a calculation.
可不是随意摆的
It wasn't just where I dropped them.
对不起
Sorry.
您还记得有一年圣诞节
Do you remember that one Christmas
我们的露天晚会上见到了一个巨人吗
when we had the giant in the pageant?
在教区里 我记得
Here in the parish? I do.
"我是个巨人"
"I am a giant."
"我叫马林斯派克"
"My name is Marlinspike."
约翰娜姑母说我们今年不举办主显节宴会了
Aunt Johane says we won't have the Epiphany Feast this year.
没办法
We can't.
没人会赴约的
No-one would come.
因为大主教被罢黜了?
Because of the Cardinal's disgrace?
剑桥的那帮书呆子笑话我的灵缇犬
People in Cambridge are laughing at my greyhounds.
为什么?
Why?
因为它们是黑色的
Because they're black.
但它们本应是白色的
They should be white.
他们说 "只有恶霸才会养能在夜里潜行的黑土狗"
They say, "Only felons have dogs that you can't see at night."
呵呵
Aha.
听着
Look.
"我是个巨人"
"I am a giant.
"我的名字是马林斯派克"
"My name is Marlinspike."
"额啊啊啊啊啊！"
"Grrrr!"
我的狗会伤害这猫的
The dogs will kill it.
你觉得他怕我么?
Do you think he's afraid of me?
为什么要怕你?
Why should he be?
我不清楚
I don't know.
和其他人在一起的时候 他看起来很活跃...
With everybody else,he seems so lively...
而当他看见我的时候...
but when he sees me...
你是个慈爱的父亲
You're a kind father.
也许有点太过溺爱 都惯坏了他
Too much so, I think. You spoil him.
莉兹也经常这么说
That's what Liz always said.
当莉兹和我还是小女孩的时候 我们一无所有
Liz and I had nothing when we were girls.
没有梳子 更别提镜子
Not a comb. Never had a mirror.
我记得他还只是一个襁褓中的婴儿时
I remember when he was a baby and I used to warm his shirt
我经常拿着他的衬衣站在火炉旁烤暖和
for him in front of the fire.
莉兹会跟我说 "别这样 他都被你宠坏了"
Liz would say "Don't do that. He'll expect it every day."
屋里有个婴儿哭闹的日子是一去不复返了
Seems such a long time since there was a baby in the house.
别盯着我看
Don't look at me.
难道约翰 威廉姆森没有同你行夫妻之事吗?
Does John Williamson not do his duty by you?
和他同房非我所愿
His duty's not my pleasure.
真不该嘴贱提这事
There's a conversation I shouldn't have had.
我是里奥斯利
Wriothesley.
应该这么拼...
It's spelled W-R-I-O-T- ...
呃...叫我里斯利就好
Just call me Risley.
里斯利学士 我们一直在找前途光明的小伙子
Master Risley, we're always looking for bright young men.
- 你曾替主教效过力吧？ - 是的 先生
-You worked for the Cardinal, I think? -Yes, sir.
但又去跟了史蒂芬 伽迪纳？
But then left with Stephen Gardiner?
只是帮他管帐而已
I'm his clerk.
并不占用我的全部时间
But it doesn't occupy all my time
我一直想有机会能学习经商之道 先生
and I'm keen to learn something of business, sir.
呵呵 我们奥斯汀兄弟会 一直都忙着做买卖 是不 孩子们
Oh, we're all business here at Austin Friars... aren't we, boys?
你早知道伽迪纳 会派他来监视我们的吧
You know Gardiner will have sent him here to spy on us.
他看起来还挺有礼貌的
Well, he seems obliging.
也许我们可以试试反间计
Perhaps we could send him back to spy on Gardiner.
他怎么样了
How's he been?
他一直在鞭笞自己？
He's whipping himself?
几个修道士给他的
The monks who come to him brought it.
我的上帝啊！
Body of Christ.
这些到底是谁做的
Who makes these things?
能将荆棘和马鬃系在一起
Who ties a thorn to horse hair?
做这玩意儿真是太屈才了
People ought to be found better jobs.
决定了 我们要赶紧带他离开这
That settles it, we have to get him out of here.
天呐
Oh, oh, God.
在约克郡他的处境会好很多
He'd be better off in Yorkshire.
但我们会承受什么代价呢
But how would we pay for it?
不过要是你能见到国王...
If only you would see the King...
帮我传个口信给沃尔西 好吗
Take a message for me to Wolsey, will you?
有个布里多尼[法国地名]的商人抱怨说 八年前他的船
There's a Breton merchant who's complaining that his ship
被没收了 至今尚未得到赔偿
was seized eight years ago and he still hasn't received compensation.
当时的笔录文件找不到了
No-one can find the paper work.
我记得这是主教当时负责的案子
The Cardinal would have handled the case.
- 你觉得他还记得吗   - 他一定记得
- Do you think he'll remember it?  - I'm sure he will.
应该是那艘舱室中满载着
That'll be the one with powdered pearls for ballast
珍珠粉还藏有独角兽角的船
and unicorns' horns in its hold.
是 就是那艘船
Yes, that'll be the one.
陛下 如果这件案子有疑点的话 我可以跟进案情吗
If the case is in doubt, sir, may I look into it?
我不认为你有这个资格
I don't think you have a locus standi in the matter.
亨利 让他去吧
God, let him, Harry.
等这家伙结案了 那个布里多尼人可还要付大笔酬谢费的
By the time this fellow's finished, the Breton'll be paying you.
说些为你好的话
I'll say this for you.
你是主教的附属品
You stick by your man.
除了主教的恩情 我一无所有
I never had anything but kindness from the Cardinal.
你没有别的依靠了？
You have no other master?
一千英镑?
1,000 pounds?
不要说出去
Don't tell anyone.
我只能帮到这儿了
It's the best I can do.
接受我的好意去吧
Take it with my blessing.
也请他为我祈祷
And ask him to pray for me.
我无时无刻不在想念着约克大主教
Every day, I miss the Cardinal of York.
一个能从国王那里拿到一千英镑的人...
A man who can get ￡1,000 from the King...
噢 比起过去十年他亏欠主教的 还不到九牛一毛
Oh, it's only a tenth of what he's owed the Cardinal for over a decade.
花这点钱就罢黜了一个红衣主教 对他很值了
And not so much when you have a cardinal to move.
你自己又倒贴了多少进去呢
How much of your own money will you put into this?
帐不是这么算的
Some debts are not to be reckoned.
我最近倒是听到了关于某个你认识的人的流言
I heard a rumour recently about someone you know.
托马斯 怀特
Thomas Wyatt.
怀特和安妮夫人
Wyatt and the Lady Anne.
老生常谈了
It's an old story.
老生常谈吗 那国王怎么从未听过这个故事?
If it's such an old story, why hasn't the King heard it?
也许经国治世之道 就是明白何时充耳不闻
Part of the art of ruling, perhaps. Know when to shut your ears.
英国人可真是奇怪
Aren't the English odd?
谁说不是呢
Christ, aren't they?!
哈
Hmm.
不过你是懂的吧？
But you understand, I think?
她对你感兴趣
She interests you?
一个安妮都能成为王后的混乱世界里
A world where Anne can be queen
那克伦威尔能成为...？
is a world where Cromwell can be...?
亨顿和罗伊斯顿 亨廷顿 彼得伯勒（英国东部城市）
Hendon and Royston, Huntingdon, Peterborough.
我已经让车马辎重现行 一切都会为你打点好的
I've sent riders on ahead so everything will be ready for you.
这只是战术性撤退
This is a tactical retreat.
并不是投降
Not a surrender.
想赢回亨利的重用 安妮夫人才是关键
Lady Anne is the key to winning back Henry.
嗯..
Mm-hm..
汤姆 你要想办法赢得她的信任
Find a way into her confidence, Tom.
想办法哄她开心
Work a device to please her.
唯一能让安妮夫人开心的办法 就是为她戴上英格兰王后的宝冠
The only way to please that lady is to crown her Queen of England.
- 你会到北边来吗？ - 嗯哼
- Will you come north?  - Mm-hm.
只要国王传召您回来 我会亲身去接您回来 他一定会的
I'll come and fetch you, as soon as he summons you back. And he will.
上帝保佑你...
God bless you...
我挚爱的克伦威尔
mine own entirely beloved Cromwell.
托马斯？
Thomas?
我离开之后再看
Oh, er, when I'm gone.
把主教宫殿里的所有东西都搬走
I want the whole of the Archbishop's palace scrubbed out.
大人只习惯睡自己的床
My lord will be bringing his own bed.
厨房员工从国王近侍中挑选
Draft in kitchen staff from the King's Arms.
算了 还是我亲自去吧
I think I should go myself.
不不 我们可以做好的
No, we can do it.
好吧 检查...帮我拿一下
Well, check... Can you take this?
去检查下马厩
Check the stabling.
再请些乐师来
And get in musicians.
上次我经过时 那还有些柴垛还是猪圈什么的
Last time I passed through, there were some pigsties
还有一些不应该存在于宫殿之内的东西
or something against the palace wall.
- 看看是谁的 打点一下 全部清除   - 先生...
- Find the owner, pay him off, knock 'em down.  -Sir...
是时候让主教离开了
It's time to let the cardinal go.
记得我们初次见面时
You know the first time we met,
你还是个年轻的学生
was when you were a young student.
- 在哪来着？ - 兰贝斯宫
- Where was this?  - Lambeth Palace.
我叔叔约翰 曾是那里的厨师
My uncle John was the cook there
我在那儿也做过几天帮工
and I worked some days in the kitchens.
有一次是为你服务的
I served you once.
我都没什么印象了
I don't think so.
我记得有天晚上 我们在踢球
I remember, one evening we were playing football
突然 我听到有人在演奏竖笛...
and I heard a recorder playing...
我的另一位客人
Ah, my other guest...
你先抱着...
Now, you carry on...
亨利 别打扰伽迪纳大人
Now, Henry, leave Master Gardiner alone.
跟我回屋里面去 走吧 快点
You come along to the house. Come on, come on.
走吧 快进屋里
Let's go, let's go to the house.
好了好了
There.
关于里奥斯利学士...
About Master Wriothesley...
也祝你晚上好 史蒂芬
And a good evening to you, Stephen.
跟我提个醒 他是为我干活还是你?
Remind me, is he working for me, or for you?
我觉得他是你的人
For you, I would have thought?
那他为什么总在你家出没?
Then why is he always at your house?
他又不是学徒
Well, he's not a bound apprentice.
他想来就来 想走就走
He can come and go as he pleases.
我猜他想发大财
He thinks he'll make his fortune, I suppose.
大家都知道你富甲一方
Everyone knows money sticks to your hands.
他想从你这个...不管你怎么称呼自己...
He wants to know what he can learn from...
学到点小花招
whatever it is you call yourself these days.
我只是一个普通人而已
A person.
诺尔福克公爵说我只是一个普通人
The Duke of Norfolk says I'm a person.
那个就是他的傻儿子吗?
Is that his fool?
他本该是从教堂屋顶摔下来 头先着地
He's supposed to have fallen off a church roof and landed on his head.
- "本该是"?  C 如果那件事不是意外的话 就更让人糟心了
- Supposed to?  - It would be just like More to keep a fool who wasn't.
只会让人愈加尴尬
Just to embarrass people.
亨利 帕丁森 今晚好像特别激动呢
Henry Pattinson is excitable tonight.
希望他吃的别那么油腻
I hope his diet has not been too rich.
我就不担心油腻的问题...
No anxieties on that score...
他们说汀代尔在汉堡[德国城市]一直在被监视着
Tyndale has been sighted in Hamburg, they say.
如果你看到他 你能认出来吧
You'd know him, if you saw him, I suppose?
你也一样吧
So would you, I suppose?
我希望能找到个办法对付他
I hope to get the means to proceed against him
针对他书里的那些反叛言论
for sedition in his writing.
你真的在汀代尔的书中看到了反叛言论吗
Have you found sedition in Tyndale's writing?
很好
Very good.
你听见了吗 史蒂芬
You hear that, Stephen?
无名小律师才会说 "我读了汀代尔的书
A lesser lawyer would have said, "I have read Tyndale,
没发现什么不对劲的地方呀"
"and I find no fault there."
但托马斯可没有这么好骗哦
But Thomas will not be tripped, will he?
我承认 我读过汀代尔的书
Well, I admit, I have read Tyndale.
还逐字推敲了他那所谓的译文
I have picked apart his so-called translations.
我也读过路德的书[马丁 路德 德国基督神学家]
I have also read Luther.
路德就是坨翔
他的嘴就像菊花一样 屎臭世间
你的拉丁语说的非常优雅
You have such a pretty way with Latin.
那么 "近墨者黑"
So, "He that toucheth pitch shall be defiled."
除非此人是托马斯 莫尔
Unless his name is Thomas More.
呵 沃尔西总说你是《圣经》的狂热崇拜者
There you are, Wolsey always told me you were a man of the Bible.
托马斯 克伦威尔 你为什么没有再娶妻了呢
Thomas Cromwell, why don't you marry again?
没人看得上我 爱丽丝夫人
No-one will have me, Lady Alice.
胡说 你的主人也许是垮台了 但你并不穷啊
Nonsense. Your master may be down, but you're not poor.
而且你的一切现在都还算井然有序 不是吗
And you've got everything below in good working order, haven't you?
爱丽丝! 我跟你说喝酒时要注意什么来着?
Alice! What have I told you about drinking wine?
你都喝的红光满面了!
Your nose is glowing!
我为什么要带你去威斯敏斯特来着
Why am I bringing you to Westminster?
我要去见安妮夫人
I'm off to see Lady Anne.
你之前可没这么说
You didn't say so.
我不会把所有计划都告诉你的 史蒂芬
I can't tell you all my plans, Stephen.
不然年轻的里奥谢思利 可就没事做了
What would young Wriothesley have to do, then?
噢 天哪 我要饿死了!
Oh, dear God, I'm starving!
真希望那小白兔还在 我就能把它生吞活剥了
I wish I'd lain hands on the white rabbit, I'd eat it raw.
你知道莫尔每晚九点准时入睡吗
Did you know that More goes to bed at nine o'clock every night?
和爱丽丝一起?
With Alice?
当然不是
Apparently not.
你从未想过结婚吗 史蒂芬
Don't you ever think of getting married, Stephen?
我是神职人员
I'm in holy orders.
得了吧 你肯定有女人的
Oh, come on. You must have women.
没有过？！
Don't you?
你这简直是个毫无意义的反问！
What kind of a... Putney enquiry is that?!
啊 是你
Ah, it's you.
我喜欢你这身...灰色天鹅绒
I like your... grey velvet.
你在哪买的?
Where did you get it?
意大利
Italy.
能给我买点吗?
Can you get me some?
我很久没有新衣服了
It's been so long since I had new clothes.
如果你是在等她 我得提醒你 她正在大发雷霆
If you're waiting for HER, I should warn you, she's in a temper.
- 啊哈  C安妮嫌她上位的速度太慢了
- Ah-ha.  - Nothing happens quickly enough for Anne.
你觉得她会开心
You'd think she'd be happy.
你知道 当国王第一次注意到她时 国王想的是
You know, when the king first turned his attention to her, he thought,
她既然那么了解法国的那些事
knowing how things are done in France,
那她会接受宫里的一个特定的位置[情妇]
that she might accept a certain... position at court.
但那对安妮来说 却不知足
But that wasn't enough for Anne.
你知道她对我说过什么吗
You know what she said to me?
她说 "这不是法国 而我也没你这么傻 玛丽"
She said, "This isn't France, and I'm not a fool like you, Mary."
嗯...
Hm.
因为她...
Because she...
- 因为她知道我曾是亨利的情妇...  - 嗯...
- Because she knows I was Henry's mistress... - Hm.
...而且她也见证了我是怎么被抛弃的 她从中吸取了很多教训
.. and she sees how I am left. And she takes a lesson from it.
她发誓要嫁给他 而且无论安妮想要什么 她就一定要得到
She's vowed that she'll marry him. And what Anne wants, she'll have.
- 那你呢?  - 我?
- And you? - Me?
我只是一个被人玩弄过抛弃了的女人
I am to be swept out after supper like the old rushes.
我父亲说我是吃白饭的
My father says I'm a mouth to feed
我叔父诺尔福克说我是个贱女人
and my uncle Norfolk says I'm a whore.
我需要丈夫 来阻止他们的那些外号
I need a husband, to stop them calling me names.
要我说的话...
Well...
...你值得找一个年轻有为的英俊丈夫
.. you should ask for someone young and handsome.
自己不去争取 怎么能找到如意郎君呢
Don't ask, don't get.
不 我想找的是一个能膈应死他们的丈夫
No, what I want is a husband who upsets them.
而且不会因此丧命的丈夫
And who won't die.
是你说的要争取 我现在争取了
Don't ask, don't get.
他们会杀了你的
They'd kill you.
你说的对 他们会的
You're right. They would.
如果她传召你
If she's sent for you,
其实她是想讨好你
she means to flatter you.
她会让你从些许小事开始帮她的忙
She's going to ask you to do some little thing for her.
然后让你为她所用 听我的话
And then she'll make you hers. Take my advice.
在她有所行动之前 快逃走吧
Before she does, turn around and walk the other way.
弄点欢快的音乐好嘛
Cheer it up, can't you?
你刚刚做了什么?
What did you just do?
我就碰了马克 史密顿一下
I hit Mark Smeaton.
- 只用了一根手指而已   - 谁？
- But only with one finger. - Who?
噢 原来乐师叫这名字
Oh. Is that his name?
你去哪了
Where've you been?
乌托邦
Utopia.
噢 谈的怎么样
Oh. What was the talk?
女人的阴暗面
The vices and follies of women.
我想你应该聊的很开心吧
I suppose you joined in?
我的牧师 克莱姆
My chaplain. Dr Cranmer.
他躲在一边 因为没什么好消息
Hiding. Because there's no good news.
他刚从罗马回来
He's just back from Rome.
我听说罗马会颁布教令 要求国王离开我
I hear that Rome will issue a decree telling the king to part from me?
- 那是罗马犯的错   - 必须是的
- That would be a mistake on Rome's part. - Yes, it would.
他也不会听之任之的
Because he won't be told.
当他是什么了 一小屁孩儿吗
What is he? Some child?
我读过汀代尔的书
I've read Tyndale.
国民必须绝对服从国王 就如他会听从上帝一样
The subject must obey his king as he would God.
你说我理解的准确吗
Do I have the sense of it?
教皇会清楚他的地位的
The Pope will learn his place.
您传召我来什么事呢
Why did you send for me?
我有东西给你看...
I've something to show you...
- 拜托 不要把它... - 拿出来！
- Oh, please, don't give it currency...  - Give it!
这在我床上发现的
This was in my bed.
那个白脸下人给我换床单的时候发现的
The sickly milk-faced creeper had turned down the sheet.
当然 我从她身上什么也没问出来
Of course, I can't get any sense out of her,
她连被别人斜眼盯着都受不了
she cries if you look at her sideways,
所以我不知道是谁把这玩意放在我床上的
so I don't know who put it there.
看到了吗 那是凯瑟琳王后
That's the Queen, Katherine, you see?
而这个是我
And that's me.
无头的安妮
Anne sans tete.
我总听说沃尔西之所以留着你
I am told that Wolsey kept you
是因为伦敦的八卦消息都逃不出你的耳朵
because you always knew the London gossip.
如果你能查出这事是谁做的 希望你能如实禀告我
If you find out who is responsible for this, I want you to tell me.
我有了一个新的座右铭 你知道吗
I have a new motto. Did you know?
(法语)"Ainsi sera, Groigne qui groigne."
"任谁怨声载道 我亦一往无前"
"Never mind who grudges it, this will happen."
我注定要得到国王的心
I mean to have him.
这就是容易被吓哭的那位 别斜眼盯着她看
I think this is the one that cries,so don't look at her sideways.
- 克伦威尔大人 - 好久没见了
-Master Cromwell.-I haven't seen you for a long time.
你一直都在干嘛 都去哪了
What have you been doing? Where have you been?
缝纫
Sewing.
在我被遣送的地方
Where I'm sent.
还有监视别人 对吧
And spying, too, I think?
我可不擅长监视 而且也不会说法语
I'm not very good at it. I don't speak French.
所以您就别拷问我了 我没什么可报告的
So, please, don't you. It gives me nothing to report.
那你认识克莱姆牧师吗
You know Dr Cranmer?
- 不认识  - 不不...
- No.  - No...
- 我是说...这位是克莱姆牧师  - 噢...
- This is Doctor Cranmer.  - Oh...
现在你该要自报家门了
Now, you're supposed to say who you are.
约翰 西摩的女儿 来自狼厅
John Seymour's daughter, from Wolf Hall.
祝你好运吧 我尽量只用英语来进行这对话
Well, good luck. I'll try to keep the conversations in English.
真的万分感激呢
I would be obliged.
你现在要回剑桥吗
You're going back to Cambridge now?
很遗憾不能久留 博林一家希望我呆在他们身边
Sadly, not to stay. The Boleyn family likes to have me close.
呃 诺尔福克公爵怎么样了
How, erm, how is the Duke of Norfolk?
他正在气头上
He's in a fury.
为什么
About what?
他听说红衣大主教阁下已经到了索斯维尔
He heard your cardinal has reached Southwell
人们从各地涌来就为了看他一眼
and the crowds have come flocking from far and wide just to see him.
简直像一支凯旋归来的军队
As if it were a triumphal procession.
他应该...也许...
He should... perhaps...
更加小心谨慎点
be more cautious.
如果国王能生一次气
If the king was offended once,
就还会有第二次
he can be offended again.
她长什么样呢
So, what's she like?
安妮夫人
The Lady Anne?
高还是矮
Tall or short?
不高不矮
Neither.
他们说她舞跳得很好
They say she dances well.
我们没跳过
We didn't dance.
她牙齿好吗
Are her teeth good?
等她用它们咬我的时候
When she sinks them into me,
我会告诉你的
I'll let you know.
似乎你已经靠她很近了
Sounds like you've got close enough.
为何上帝要如此考验我们?
Why does God test us?
我也不认为我们能通过考验
I don't think we'll pass.
条件还有待提高
Conditions could be better.
他希望你可以送点鹌鹑过去
Um, he wondered if you could send quails?
- 那儿的食物太难吃了  - 我提醒过他了
- The food is deplorable up there.  - I did warn him.
托马斯 无论走到哪 人们都蜂拥而来
Everywhere he goes, Thomas, they flock to see him.
成千上万的人
Thousands of them!
他的昔日雄风又回来了
You can see his old spirit returning.
他在北部教堂召开了教士会议
He's called a convocation of the northern church.
没有通知国王吗
Without informing the king?
他说 "呵 乔治 他们没必要知道"
He said, "Ah, George, why do they need to know."
这是独立的信号 没别的意思
It's a signal of independence, that's all.
有人会说这是傲慢自负的信号
Some might say a signal of pride.
我知道
I know.
我知道人们在议论什么
I know what people are saying.
说我现在一个人单干了
That I'm working for myself now,
说我被收买了
that I've been bought out.
如果你能去向他解释 那么所有疑虑都...
If you came and spoke to him, any doubts that he has...
这里需要我
I'm needed here.
来保护他
To protect him.
来说服国王
To persuade the king.
他仍喜欢我的 乔治
He likes me, George.
我能感受的到
I feel it.
当他能听进我的话 主教就会被召回
And when I have his ear, the cardinal will be recalled.
我保证
I promise you.
如果他不幸去世怎么办?
What if he dies?
如果他摔下马脖子折了怎么办?
What if he falls off his horse and breaks his neck?
几年前 一个负责国王的饮食起居的小伙
Few years ago, this fella here, charged the king in the lists,
把长矛向国王的头盔刺去...砰...
runs his lance into the king's headpiece...bam...
长矛在离眼睛一英寸的地方碎掉了
lance shatters, an inch, just an inch, from his eye.
一年后 国王带着他的猎鹰外出
Year later, king's out with his hawk,
经过一处沟渠时 撑了一根杆渡渠
comes to a ditch, drives a pole in to help him cross.
走一半那该死的杆子断了
Damn thing breaks and there he is,
他就脸朝下陷进泥潭中 差点淹死
face down in a foot of mud, drowning.
要不是一个仆人救了他 那现在执政的会是谁呢?
If a servant hadn't pulled him out, who would reign, then?
他有一个嫡出的孩子
He has one child born in wedlock.
- 谁 玛丽么 那个小虾米?  - 她总会长大的
- What, Mary? The talking shrimp?   - Well, she'll grow up.
我们还需等待 她的头还只有我指甲这么大
We're still waiting. Head's the size of my fingernail.
一个女人戴上国王王冠可不是自然而然的事
And a woman on the English throne flies in the face of nature.
何况女人无法指挥军队
A woman can't lead an army.
她祖母就这么干过
Her grandmother did.
克伦威尔 你在干什么
Cromwell what are you doing
偷听绅士间的谈话吗
listening to the conversations of gentlemen?
那个把国王从泥沼里救出来的仆人
The servant who dragged the king out of the ditch.
是谁?
What was his name?
克伦威尔学士总喜欢打听这些下等人的事哦
Master Cromwell likes to hear of the deeds of those of low birth.
他叫 爱德蒙 莫迪
His name was Edmund Mody.
听着怎么像"烂泥巴"...哈！
"Muddy" more like! Haha!
眼力过人嘛
You've a good eye.
臂力也不错
A good arm.
这个距离...我还可以应付...
Well, at this distance...
我家里面 每周天都会比赛
We have a match every Sunday, my household.
我们和公会成员们碰面
We meet up with our fellow guildsmen,
然后去肉店和杂货店里搞破坏
and we destroy the butchers and the grocers!
不如下次我跟你同去如何
What if I came down with you one week?
只是微服出游?
In disguise?
国王是需要时不时炫耀一下自己的能力的 你觉得呢
A king should show himself sometimes, don't you think?
我可以轮替你出场比试射箭
I could shoot for you!
那...那我们肯定会赢的
Well, well, we'd win for sure!
沃尔西曾告诉过我你貌似很厌恶宗教生活
Wolsey told me once that you had a loathing of those in religious life?
这是为什么他觉得你对修道院的监察
That's why he found you so diligent
如此孜孜不倦的原因吗
in your inspection of the monasteries?
不是那个原因
That was not the reason.
- 我能说两句么? - 老天 真是求之不得
- May I speak?  - God, I wish someone would!
如果你问我对修道士的看法
If you ask me about the monks,
我会说说我的经验之谈 而不是偏见
I speak from experience, not prejudice,
而我的过往经历来看 他们都腐败且浪费
and my experiences have largely been one of corruption and waste.
我亲眼见他们过得像勋爵大人
I've seen monks who live like great lords
吃着穷人们的救济粮
on the offerings of the poor,
不停接收新的孩子
take children in,
但却不像承诺般一样给他们优良教育
and rather than educating them as they promise,
把孩子们当作仆人 几千年来 修道士们已经在历史中
use them as servants. For hundreds of years, the monks have written
记载了我们被夺去的东西
what we take to be our history.
但他们却只是阻碍了真实的历史进程
I think they've suppressed our true history,
只攥写罗马教廷希望看的篇章
and written one which is favourable to Rome.
他们每年进贡给教廷的钱
I could make good use of the money
要是给我 肯定能派上大用处
that flows from them to Rome each year.
弗朗斯瓦国王比我富裕的多
King Francois is richer than I am.
他可以随意收税
He taxes his subjects as he pleases.
而我却要召集议会来征求意见 否则就会有暴动
I have to call parliament or there are riots.
恕我直言 陛下 弗朗斯瓦太嗜战
Well, sir, with respect, Francois likes war too much
而无视了贸易的重要性
and trade too little.
若贸易顺利的话 将能征得更多的税收
There are more taxes to be raised when trade is good.
而即使有教会的教令 拒绝纳税
And if taxes are resisted, even by the Church
我们也能有其他的解决办法
other ways can be found.
好吧
All right.
有时间来跟我的律师们坐下来谈谈吧
Sit down with my lawyers to discuss it.
从修道院开始
Begin with the monasteries.
一些人说我应该考虑解除婚姻关系
Some say that I should consider my marriage dissolved
然后我就能尽快娶我真正想要的女人了
and I should remarry as I please. And soon.
- 但还有另一帮人说...  - 我就是那帮人中的一个
- But there are others who say... - I am one of the others.
我的天 我不会因这些闲言碎语而怯懦的！
Dear Christ, I shall be unmanned by it!
我还有等多久?!
How long am I supposed to wait?!
安妮说她要离我而去
Anne says she'll leave me.
说她已经有了别的男人
Says there are other men.
说她现在这样是在浪费她的青春
Says she's wasting her youth.
开门！
Open up!
我是国王的人 开门！
It's the king's men. Open up!
发生什么事了 是来抓我们的么
What is it? Is it an arrest?
- 早上好 威廉 布里尔顿   - 随时待命
- Good morning, William Brereton. - I'm here if you need me.
您这是早起还是晚睡 先生? 你带孩子们去睡觉
Are you up early, or down late, sir? Take the girls to bed.
走吧 孩子们
Come, girls.
国王在格林威治 你得现在过去一趟
The king is at Greenwich. You're to come now.
那所有人都上床睡觉去吧
Well, then, everybody, back to bed.
国王请我去格林威治 就肯定不是为了抓我
The king wouldn't invite me to Greenwich in order to arrest me.
逮捕也不是这么个逮捕法
It doesn't happen that way.
他找我要做什么?
What does he want me for?
恕不奉告
I really can't enlighten you.
哈利 诺里斯
Harry Norris.
克伦威尔大人 我们总在奇怪的状况下见面
Master Cromwell, we do meet under the strangest circumstances.
你一个人跟我进去
You, only, to come in.
他在等你
He's waiting.
你待在这
You stay here.
我死去的哥哥来找我了
My dead brother came to me.
他看起来还好吗
How did he look?
就像记忆中的那样 不过脸色惨白
As I remember him. But he was pale.
骨瘦如柴
And thin.
而且有一团白色冥火围绕着他
There was a white fire around him.
他逝于勒德落 正值寒冬
He died in Ludlow, in winter.
当时道路不通
The roads were impenetrable.
只能把他的棺材放在牛车上
They had to put his coffin on an ox cart.
我从没有机会瞻仰他的遗容
I never saw him dead.
直到今晚
Until tonight.
死去之人不会托梦回来抱怨葬礼的
The dead don't come back to complain of their burial.
他很悲伤
He was so sad.
他回来是为了让我羞愧
He's come back to make me ashamed.
抢了他的王座
For taking his kingdom.
还利用他的妻子
Using his wife.
如果陛下的哥哥在继位之前就去世了
If Your majesty's brother died before he could reign...
..那便是天意如此
.. then that was God's will.
至于您的婚姻
And as for your supposed marriage,
我们都知道是清白的 虽违悖圣经
we all know that that was clean,contrary to the scriptures.
但上帝有灵
But with God,
- 已足够仁慈了... - 那又不是对我仁慈!
- there's mercy enough... - Not for me!
每当我自己做出判断的时候
When I come to my judgment,
他就会来反驳我
he will plead against me.
他现在回来是想让我难堪...
He has come to make me ashamed...
...我却孤身一人 默默忍受
.. and I alone must bear it.
我...
I...
我孤身一人
I alone.
您哥哥跟你谈了什么
Did your brother speak to you?
有什么暗示吗
Make any sign?
没有
No.
那你就是过度揣测你哥哥的想法了
Then you have read into his face something that wasn't there.
听着
Listen to me.
你知道亚瑟王的墓碑上刻着什么吗
You know what's written on Arthur's tomb?
(拉丁语)
"Rex quondam rexque futurus."
"一朝为王 永世为王"
"King once, and king to be."
你的父亲做到了这句话 他从流放归来
Your father made it sure.He came back from exile,
夺回了失去的权力
claimed his ancient right.
但这王位并不稳当 您得掌控住它
But it's not enough to claim a country, you have to hold it.
并将它世代传承下去
It has to be made secure,in every generation.
如果您哥哥回来好像是在责怪你
If your brother comes back and seems to say
夺了他的王国 他的王位
that you have taken his kingdom, taken his place,
那是因为他想让您成为他曾想登上的王位
it's because he wants YOU to become the king he would have been.
他不能世代传承王位
He can't fulfil the prophecy,
因为他是威尔士出身的王子
a prince come out of Wales,
但他希望您能继承王位
but he wills you to do it.
那他现在为什么又回来了?
But why does he come back now?
我都当了20年国王
I have been king for 20 years.
因为现在是关键时期
Because now is the vital time.
现在是时候 您表现出王霸之气
Now is the time for you to become the king you should be,
表现出唯吾独尊的上位者的气势
the sole and supreme head of your kingdom.
问问安妮
Ask Anne.
她也会这么说
She'll say the same.
确实如此
She does.
她说我们不应臣服于罗马
She says we should not bow to Rome.
如果您父亲也向您托梦
And if your father should come to you in your dream,
您也要这样想
you take it the same way as you take this one.
他们是来辅佐您的
They come to strengthen your hand.
我懂了
I see.
真的都懂了
I understand it all now.
我知道派谁去了
I knew who to send for.
我一直都该知道的
I always do.
发生什么事了
What happened?
国王做了个梦
The king had a dream.
做梦?
A dream?
他半夜把我们叫醒 就因为一个梦?
He got us out of bed for a dream?
相信我 他还有别的原因的
Oh, believe me, he gets one out of bed for far less than that.
是个噩梦吗
Was it a bad dream?
"是噩梦吗"
"Was it a bad dream?"
他本来是这么认为的
He thought it was.
但现在不是了
It isn't now.
你的孩子们很爱你
Your children love you.
没有这个带头人 我们也都做不成事的
We can't do without the man in charge.
克雷默先生 告诉安娜夫人
Dr Cranmer, tell the Lady Anne
我们今晚替她办了件大好事
we did a good night's work for her tonight.
保持安静
Quietly now.
别又把大家吵醒了
Don't wake the house a second time.
很好
Well done.
你没事吧
Safe?
嗯
Mm.
我还以为...
I thought...
什么?
What?
我还以为要来清算了
I thought it was going to be a reckoning.
清算什么
A reckoning?
为了什么
For what?
不知道 所有的这一切吧
I don't know. All the things.
这些画 书 鲁特琴 还有些不认识的东西
The paintings, the books and lutes, and I don't know what.
我们现在所拥有的一切
The things we have now.
先生你真是个罗马乞丐!
You, sir, are a Roman pauper!
先生你真是个佛莱芒大胖子
Sir, you are a fat Fleming,
面包上还抹着黄油
and spread butter on your bread.
先生 愿您的后代都吃蜗牛
Well, sir, may your offspring eat snails.
叫我里斯利！
Call Me Risley!
给你画下来应该很不错 里奥谢思利学士！你在这干嘛
You look fit to be painted, Master Wriothesley! What are you about?
等孩子们 他们今早很有兴致呢
Waiting on the children. They're in high spirits this morning.
啦啦啦啦...啦啦啦...
La la la la, la la la...
哼的那是什么调
What's that?
以前我在意大利的时候学的小曲
It's a tune from my days in Italy.
我还记得...
I remember...
他从不说他自己的故事
He never tells stories about himself.
好吧...我...呃...
Well, well... I, erm...
在意大利的时候 我和...
When I was in Italy, me and the...
我和那些波尔蒂纳里家的男孩们
.. me and the Portinari boys,
波尔蒂纳里家的男孩们
the Portinari boys,
我们做了个雕像
we had a statue made,
挥舞着翅膀傻笑的上帝小雕像
a little smirking god with wings.
我们用锤子和链条敲打它 还雇了个骡夫 把雕像运到罗马
We beat it with hammers and chains,hired a muleteer and drove it to Rome
还冒充是奥古斯都时期的古董 卖给了一个红衣大主教
and sold it to a cardinal as an antique from the reign of Augustus.
我还记得...
I remember...
当他付我们钱时 眼里还噙着泪水
he. he had tears in his eyes when he paid us.
当波尔蒂纳里家的男孩们回佛罗伦萨时
And when the Portinari
boys went back to Florence
他们因为钱袋太重 路都走不稳了
they were staggering under
the weight of their purses.
- 那你做了什么  - 什么
- What did you do?  - What?
分了我那份钱 留下来接着卖拖鞋 不然呢
Took my cut, and stayed on to sell the mules, what do you think?
（意大利语）? Scaramella会有战争 ?
(Italian) ? Scaramella va alla guerra ?
（意大利语）? 长矛啊 武器啊 ?
(Italian) ? Colla lancia et la rotella ?
我们还未用完晚餐
We hadn't finished dinner.
他们就来了
They came in,
他们从门房那里拿了钥匙
they'd taken the keys from the porter.
他们已经在楼梯口设了哨兵
They'd already set sentries on the stairs.
是谁
Who was it?
哈利 珀西
Harry Percy.
他浑身发抖
He was shaking.
我就想 "为什么要派他 为什么是哈利 珀西"'
I thought, "Why send him? Why Harry Percy?"'
然后我想起...
Then I thought...
安妮夫人 你还记得吗
Lady Anne, you remember,
她那时只是个女孩
she was just a girl.
她想嫁给他
She wanted to marry him.
红衣主教阁下却阻止了
The cardinal stopped it.
这是在复仇
Revenge.
她已经等候多时了
She waited her time.
哈利
Harry,
要是知道你来 我会等你共进晚餐的
if I'd known, I would have waited dinner for you.
貌似鱼都快吃光了
I fear we've almost finished the fish.
- 我要祈祷奇迹发生吗  - 大人，我以叛国罪逮捕你
- Shall I pray for a miracle?   - My lord, I arrest you for high treason.
逮捕令呢
Your warrant?
我自有王命在身 但非你可看
There are items in my instructions you may not see.
如若你不把它展示出来
Well, if you won't show it,
恐怕我是不会屈服的
I won't surrender to you.
所以...
So...
就是这么个情况
here's a state of affairs!
走吧 乔治
Come, George.
看着我 乔治
Look at me, George.
我不惧怕任何生者
I'm not afraid of any man alive.
呃...
Um...
恩...
Er...
他们把我们从房子里带走 向南走
They took us from the house, rode south.
有一群人在等着见他 举着蜡烛
There were crowds waiting to see him, holding candles.
我们以为他们会散去 但他们整晚都站在路中央
We thought they'd disperse, but they just stood all night in the road.
他绝食了
He stopped eating.
为什么
Why?
我不知道
I don't know.
有人说...有人说他想毁灭自己
Some said... some said he wanted to destroy himself.
一切发生的太快了
It all happened so fast.
之后金斯顿来了
And then Kingston came.
我不得不告诉他 托马斯
I had to tell him, Thomas.
我不得不告诉我们大人 象牙塔的那个治安官
I had to tell our lord that the Constable of the Tower
已经来带走他了
had come to fetch him.
他只是重复问道"威廉 金斯顿?"
He just kept saying "William Kingston?"
一遍又一遍 好像他不敢相信
over and over, as if he couldn't believe it.
我们抵达莱斯特时
By the time we reached Leicester
他虚弱的站都站不住
he was too ill to stand.
咳出了黑色的血
He voided black blood.
我认为...是有人下毒...
I thought... poison...
托马斯...
Thomas...
他马上来了 大人
He's coming, my lord.
他在哪儿?
Where... where is he?
你知道克伦威尔的 大人
You know Cromwell, my lord.
他说会来 就一定会来的
If he says he'll come, he'll be here.
"对不起 托马斯"
'I'm sorry, Thomas.'
"他第二天就去世了"
'He died the next day.'
他们...
They...
他们给了他
They gave him
一个纸板糊起来的棺材
a coffin of plain boards.
市里的官员来查验了他的尸体
And the city officials came to view his body
来破除说他已经逃亡法国的谣言
so there couldn't be any false rumours that he'd escaped to France.
他们...他们还嘲笑他
They... they made jokes.
嘲笑他卑微的出身
They made jokes about his low birth!
来 沃尔西 我们接你下地狱
Come, Wolsey! We're fetching you to Hell,
我们的魔王大人
where our master, Beelzebub,
正盼着和你共进晚餐
is expecting you to supper!
魔王愿和你共享野味
Beelzebub would have you joint his venison.
他听说您可是一个屠夫的儿子
He's heard of your skill as a butcher!
"我发誓成为皇家枢密院的议员..."
'"I swear to be a true and faithful councillor..."'
"忠诚无二的效忠国王陛下"
"to the King's Majesty as one of His Highness's Privy Council."
我发誓成为皇家枢密院的议员
I swear to be a true and faithful councillor
忠诚无二的效忠国王陛下
to the King's Majesty as one of His Highness's Privy Council.
"我不会参与或做出任何"
"I shall not know or understand of any manner thing to be attempted,
"违抗或顶撞国王陛下的事情"
"done, or spoken against His Majesty's person..."
我不会参与或做出任何
I shall not know or understand of any manner thing
违抗或顶撞国王陛下的事情
to be attempted, done, or spoken against His Majesty's person.
"我立誓维护国王的威望"
'"I swear to uphold the king's authorities.
"我立誓维护国王的统治..."
'"I swear to uphold the king's jurisdictions..."
我立誓维护国王的威望
'I swear to uphold the king's authorities.
我立誓维护国王的统治
'I swear to uphold the king's jurisdictions.
"我立誓拥护国王的子嗣及法定继承人"
'"I swear to uphold the king's heirs and lawful successors."'
我立誓拥护国王的子嗣及法定继承人
I swear to uphold the king's heirs and lawful successors.
我跪在他身侧...
I knelt by his body...
为他而哭泣
.. and I wept
也向上帝祈祷 复仇降临到他们每人身上
and I prayed to God to send vengeance upon them all!
不必劳烦上帝 乔治
There's no need to trouble God, George.
我将亲手复仇
I'll take it in hand.
彼以国士待我，我以国士待之，用过免费优质字幕服务，
而又有能力的人，有义务将这个免费服务做下去若有心加入我们 联系：dajiazimuzu@163.com